CAPTAIN PEARL R. NYE COLLECTION
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Captain Pearl R. Nye Collection1937-1944
AFC 1937/002
Archive of American Folk Song
Nye, Pearl R., 1872-1950
18 folders total (Folders 1-16 and Folder 18 in 1 box, plus Folder 17, oversize).
22 sound discs: analog; 12 in.
7 photographic prints: black and white, color; various sizes.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center Library of Congress Washington, D.C. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.home
The collection is comprised of field recordings made in Akron, Ohio, by John A. Lomax (on June 27-28, 1937), and Alan Lomax and Elizabeth Lomax (on November 3, 1937), of songs performed by Pearl R. Nye related to life on the Ohio and Erie Canal, plus photographs of canal life (some hand-decorated by Nye), and correspondence between Nye and Harold Spivacke of the Library of Congress, and manuscript and typed transcriptions of song lyrics sung and collected by Pearl R. Nye.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002, collector.; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002--Correspondence.; Lomax, John A. (John Avery), 1867-1948, collector, interviewer.; Lomax, John A. (John Avery), 1867-1948--Correspondence.; Nye, Pearl R., 1872-1950, collector, interviewee.; Nye, Pearl R., 1872-1950--Correspondence.; Waterhouse, Helen Stocking, 1892-1965 -- Correspondence.
Organizations
American Folklife Center.; Archive of American Folk Song, collector.; Library of Congress. National Digital Library Program.
Subjects
Ballads, English--Ohio.; Canals--Ohio--Songs and music.; Field recordings--Ohio.; Folk music--Ohio.; Folk songs, English--Ohio.; Popular music--1931-1940.; Revival hymns--Ohio.
Places
Ohio--Akron--Social life and customs; Ohio and Erie Canal (Ohio)--Songs and music.
Titles
Captain Pearl R. Nye, life on the Ohio and Erie Canal; Pearl R. Nye collection
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Sound recordings.; Interviews.; Field recordings.
Administrative Information
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Sound Recordings; III. Graphic Materials.
Acquisition
Subsequent to the field trips, the sound recordings were accessioned at the Library of Congress. Communications between Pearl Nye and Library of Congress staff accumulated as they were received at the Library (rather than being sent as a unit, at a later date). According to correspondence, in the 1940s Nye sent more transcriptions to the Library, which were microfilmed, then returned to him. These are presumed to be the documents on the microfilm reel.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
Autograph manuscript containing song texts by Pearl R. Nye, with a few letters to Alan Lomax and to Harold Spivacke is available on microfilm [Songs of the Ohio canal, 1938], Library of Congress Music Division, MUS-12.
Electronic Format
A substantial portion of the collection is available as "Captain Pearl R. Nye, life on the Ohio and Erie Canal," an American Memory online presentation compiled by the National Digital Library Program of the Library of Congress. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000019
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Collection Concordance by Format
Manuscript Materials
17 folders Box 1, Folders 1-16, 18
1 folder Folders 17, oversize
Sound Recordings
22 12-inch lacquer-coated aluminum audio discs AFS 01001-01009, AFS 01603-01615
4 12-inch aluminum audio discs AFS 01005_dupe, AFS 01007_dupe, AFS 01605_dupe, AFS 01606_dupe
Graphic Materials
7 photographic prints: black and white, color; various sizes Box 1, Folder 18
Scope and Content
The Captain Pearl R. Nye Collection consists of materials that document the professional relationship between Pearl R. Nye and the Library of Congress, as well as the personal relationship between Nye and Alan Lomax. The collection is centered on Nye’s documentation of and contribution to folk songs about the Ohio and Erie Canal. It includes sound recordings of Nye, recorded by John A. Lomax, and Alan and Elizabeth Lomax in Akron, Ohio in 1937, correspondence between the Library of Congress and Nye, and photographs of Nye at his home on the canal.
Nye’s desire to collect canal folk songs and sing them for the Lomaxes stemmed from his childhood growing up on the canal, his own career as a canal captain, and his later years when traditional activities on the Ohio and Erie Canal were supplanted by more modern technologies.
Nye’s transcriptions of song lyrics provide an invaluable research tool. These transcriptions include those songs he sang (included on the recordings), as well as songs he knew (and were not recorded). These lyrics reflect not only popular sentiments of the times, but enduring values and traditions, as they provide a snapshot of a way of life for trade and travel that was becoming obsolete through technological advances.
Biographical History
Pearl R. Nye was born on February 5, 1872 aboard the canal boat "Reform." He spent his life on canal boats on the Ohio and Erie Canal and researched and documented the songs and traditions of canal life. He died in 1950.
http://lccn.loc.gov/2004447752
Container List
- Series I: MANUSCRIPTS
  - Collection finding aid, 8 pp. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Documentation for sound recordings, 6 pp. (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Documentation for digitization of sound recordings, 65 pp. (Box-folder 1/3)
    Various documents detailing the digitization process, including hardware and software used, plus any problems with the source recordings.
  - Correspondence, 1937, afc1937002_ms01 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Folder 1 of 2), afc1937002_ms02 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Folder 2 of 2), afc1937002_ms02 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Correspondence, 1939, afc1937002_ms03 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941, afc1937002_ms04 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Correspondence, 1942, afc1937002_ms05 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Correspondence, 1944, afc1937002_ms06 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Correspondence, undated, afc1937002_ms07 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Various correspondence, 1937 and undated, 9 pp. (Box-folder 1/12)
    Items of correspondence formerly alienated from the collection, which were returned to the collection but not digitized. The undated items may have been written in 1936.
  - Transcriptions (Folder 1 of 4), afc1937002_ms08 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Transcriptions (Folder 2 of 4), afc1937002_ms09 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Transcriptions (Folder 3 of 4), afc1937002_ms10 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Transcriptions (Folder 4 of 4), afc1937002_ms11 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Various manuscript materials, 13 items (Folder 17)
    Manuscript items formerly alienated from the collection, which were returned to the collection and subsequently treated by Conservation Division staff, but not digitized.
- Series II: SOUND RECORDINGS
  - Recorded on June 27, 1937, AFS 01001; afc1937002_sr01
    - Side A: [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - The House Carpenter
    - [Spoken segment, no. 2]
    - The Scioto Valley Mills
    - Side B: Johnny and Molly
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - My horses ain’t hungry, they won't eat your hay
  - Recorded on June 27, 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01002; afc1937002_sr02
    - Side A: Perry's Victory
    - Side B: The Girl with the striped stockings on
    - Barbara Allen
  - Recorded on June 27, 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01003; afc1937002_sr03
    - Side A: James Bird
    - Side B: Hush-a-bye-baby
    - [Spoken segment]
    - The jolly boatman
  - Recorded on June 27, 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01004; afc1937002_sr04
    - Side A: Lord Vanifer's wife
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - When I was single
    - [Spoken segment, no. 2]
    - Side B: The bold bolster
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Julianne Johnson
  - Recorded on June 27, 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01005; afc1937002_sr05
    - Side A: We’ll end this war down by the river
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - The resurrection car
    - [Spoken segment, no. 2]
    - Side B: [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Lord Vanifer's wife
  - Duplicate of recording made on June 27, 1937. Duplication date unknown., AFS 01005_dupe; afc1937002_sr06
    - Side A: We’ll end this war down by the river
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - The resurrection car
    - [Spoken segment, no. 2]
    - Side B: [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Lord Vanifer's wife
  - Recorded in 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01006; afc1937002_sr07
    - Side A: [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Dutch jollification song
    - [Spoken segment, no. 2]
    - Edward Bold
    - [Spoken segment, no. 3]
    - [Edward Bold]
    - St. Peter at the gate
    - [Spoken segment, no. 4]
    - Side B: Keep that baby still
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Over in the promised land
    - Oh, glory, hallelujah
  - Recorded in 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01007; afc1937002_sr08
    - Side A: Lord Lovele [sic]
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Jones' hospital
    - Side B: Irish washerwoman
    - Dark-eyed sailor
  - Duplicate of recording made in 1937. Duplication date unknown., AFS 01007_dupe; afc1937002_sr09
    - Side A: Lord Lovele [sic]
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Jones' hospital
    - Side B: Irish washerwoman
    - Dark-eyed sailor
  - Recorded in 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01008; afc1937002_sr10
    - Side A: Little red bird in the tree
    - Old woman under the hill
    - Side B: [Willy Reilly]
  - Recorded on June 28, 1937, in Akron, Ohio., AFS 01009; afc1937002_sr11
    - Side A: Mr. Frog
    - [Spoken segment, no.1]
    - Side B: Mary, don’t you weep
    - [Spoken segment, no. 1]
    - Little Sally Waters
    - [Spoken segment, no. 2]
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01603; afc1937002_sr12
    - Side A: The Clever Skipper
    - Side B: Gentle Little Jenny (The Wife Wrapped in the Wether's Skin)
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01604; afc1937002_sr13
    - Side A: Take a Trip on the Canal If You Want to Have Fun [continued on Side B]
    - Side B: Take a Trip on the Canal If You Want to Have Fun [continued from Side A; continued on AFS 01605a]
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01605; afc1937002_sr14
    - Side A: Take a Trip on the Canal If You Want to Have Fun [continued from AFS 01604b]
    - William was a royal lover
    - Side B: The Cumberland's crew
  - Duplicate of recording made on November 3, 1937. Duplication date unknown., AFS 01605_dupe; afc1937002_sr15
    - Side A: Take a Trip on the Canal If You Want to Have Fun [continued from AFS 01604b]
    - William was a royal lover
    - Side B: The Cumberland's crew
  - Duplicate of recording made on November 3, 1937. Duplication date unknown., AFS 01606_dupe; afc1937002_sr16
    - Side A: On the banks of Salee
    - Side B: In the shade of a tree
    - We'll outshine the sun
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01606; afc1937002_sr17
    - Side A: On the banks of Salee
    - Side B: In the shade of a tree
    - We'll outshine the sun
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01607; afc1937002_sr18
    - Side A: Riding on the elevated railroad
    - The cruel ship carpenter [continued on Side B]
    - Side B: The ship's cruel carpenter [continued from Side A]
    - Lord Ullin's daughter
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01608; afc1937002_sr19
    - Side A: Between me and the wall
    - Side B: Between me and the wall
    - Pretty Sally [continued on AFS 01609a]
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01609; afc1937002_sr20
    - Side A: Pretty Sally [continued from AFS 01608b]
    - The Jew's daughter/The Butcher boy
    - Side B: The gospel chariot
    - The dying cowboy
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01610; afc1937002_sr21
    - Side A: The roving gambler
    - Erin’s green shore
    - Side B: Dandy Jim of Caroline
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01611; afc1937002_sr22
    - Side A: The old skipper
    - Side B: Early in the spring
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01612; afc1937002_sr23
    - Side A: Rosin the bow
    - My father's broke the ice and gone
    - Side B: Who killed Cock Robin
    - I won't marry at all
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01613; afc1937002_sr24
    - Side A: I owed ten dollars to O'Grady
    - Boys, keep away from the girls
    - I say [continued on Side B]
    - Side B: Boys, keep away from the girls
    - I say [continued from Side A]
    - Just one penny
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01614; afc1937002_sr25
    - Side A: We're going to pump out Lake Erie
    - In the storm at sea
    - A canal dance (One Night in Cleveland)
    - Side B: Moonlight Dance (Yellowbud gals)
    - Canal boat wedding
    - Down the river
  - Recorded on November 3, 1937; location uncertain., AFS 01615; afc1937002_sr26
    - Side A: The gospel train
    - When the old sun was a-crawlin’
    - Jawbone (Jawbone walk, jawbone talk)
    - Side B: The banks of the sweet Dundee
- Series III: GRAPHIC MATERIALS (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Portrait of Captain Pearl R. Nye, afc1937002_ph01; Black-and-white photographic print (3” x 4.5”)
  - Captain Pearl R. Nye with B.F. Goodrich buildings in background, afc1937002_ph02; Black-and-white photographic print; hand-tinted, with a collage effect, plus a manuscript item affixed to the lower back edge of the item (4.5” x 3.5” for the photo; 2” x 3.5” for the manuscript item)
  - Captain Pearl R. Nye at Camp Charming (view from water), afc1937002_ph03; Black-and-white photographic print (5.5” x 3.5”)
  - Captain Pearl R. Nye at Camp Charming (view from land), afc1937002_ph04; Black-and-white photographic print (5.5” x 3.5”)
  - Captain Pearl R. Nye at Camp Charming (view from water, at a distance), afc1937002_ph05; Black-and-white photographic print (5.5” x 3.5”)
  - Captain Pearl R. Nye at Camp Charming (view from water, at a distance), afc1937002_ph06; Black-and-white photographic print (5.5” x 3.5”)
  - Portrait of Captain Pearl R. Nye outdoors, with women in the background, afc1937002_ph07; Color photographic print, incorporated in a collage on top of an outline of a moose (3.25” x 4.75”)